Arturo Bernal Gimeno

14 Bembibre Madrid, Spain +34 638467743 arturobernalg@gmail.com

Principal Engineer

Principal engineer with more than 13 years of experience designing, implementing and adapting backend and frontend applications using Java, angular and more technologies. Results-oriented specialized in large scale software design and development for a wide variety of companies.

Focused to continue growing in the Java industry by improving my technical skills and learning new technologies.

Able to learn new skills quickly and to find creative solutions to challenging problems. I am and passionate, responsible and committed engineer.

Technical Tools

Programming Languages	Java EE, J2EE, Spring, Oracle SQL, PL/SQL, GWT HTML, CSS3, XML, jQuery, Javascript, angularjs, JSP, Ajax, JSON. Hibernate, Spring MVC, Visual Basic and C/C++/C
Platforms & Frameworks	JEE Oracle. Apache Struts, JUnit, Spring Framework, Hibernate
OS's & IDE's	Windows, Mac OS X, Ubuntu. Eclipse, NetBeans.
Office Suite	Frequent use of the MS Office & OpenOffice suite.
Other	Maven, JUnit, jasmine.js TDD. Selenium, Jenkins, Sonar, GitHub, Ant, SOAP, REST,SOA, Mercurial, SubVersion. Bitbucket. Jenkins, JIRA, Team City. Java 6 multithreading. OOD techniques. JMS (ActiveMQ), Solace System. Apache Axis, Axis2, WSS4J, KeyTool UI Websphere, Weblogic, Tomcat, Jboss, Agile/SCRUM Methodology, Linux Shell Scripting

Professional Experience

Principal Engineer, 03/2017, Sanitas, Madrid Spain

Working in the development team to maintain the web and the mobile app that provide insurance services with angularjs and java technologies.

Achievement Highlights:

- Design, develop, integrate, test and deploy company's software.
- Execute product specification, system design, development and system integration.
- Develop new product concepts and development, deliver product prototypes.
- Conduct new technology research, concept specification and design of individual software components.

Senior Software Engineer, 11/2015 – 03/2017, GFT, Madrid Spain

Worked in the development team to create a web app to provide risk management services with angularis and java 8 technologies.

Achievement Highlights:

- Created sophisticated and high performance backend and frontend solutions for a large-scale, on-demand financial system
- Developed high-quality code, following the best coding practices
- Worked closely with the QA team to ensure quality code

Senior Software Engineer, 11/2014 - 11/2015, GFT, Madrid Spain

Developed highly performance software for the financial sector to manage trading exchange.

Achievement Highlights:

- Building and maintaining web-based application for a financial entity
- Collaborated with development, QA, product owner and scrum master to prioritize needs and produce high quality software
- Developed the JMS module to connect and receive trade from Bloomberg via Solace System and JMS queues

Senior Software Engineer, 10/2013 – 11/2014, Ricoh, Madrid Spain

Developed complex solutions for financial entity and public sector to create in-house applications, using multithreaded capability with Java EE, Oracle and others.

Achievement Highlights:

- Designed and developed the back-end module to complete software as per the requirements.
- Designed and developed the back-end connection module between Spain and Europe for the traffic fine software with web Service and SOAP Message.
- Designed and developed the WSL following the specifications of the EUCARIS system
- Designed and validated the test suite to ensure optimal code.

Senior Software Engineer, 04/2011 – 10/2013 everis, Madrid Spain

Developed Interconnect Management APCs System for Telefónica mobile operator. Provide QA support.

Achievement Highlights:

- Developed application to manage the client telephone account with java Spring and Oracle.
- Worked closely with the client for the definition of new functionality and provided possible solutions to emerging issues.

Java Developer, 05/2009 – 04/2011, Indra Space, Madrid Spain

Developed the data ground generation's system PDPC-Core. Support and maintenance for the Simulation division, in the Visual DataBase Generation System (Visual DBGS).

Achievement Highlights:

- Designed and developed the component to extract and save all the satellite data.
- Developed tool to compare SMOS satellite data.
- Maintenance and support flight simulator software. Create new api to generate maps.
- Optimize the code to increase by 25% the speed of generation of maps

Junior Developer, 05/2006 – 05/2009, everis, Madrid Spain

Development and maintenance interconnection NIBS ONO applications.

Achievement Highlights:

- Migrate from PL/SQL to Java the module to bill the call between users, increasing the processing speed.
- Create technical documentation and user's manual.
- Designed and validated the test suite to ensure optimal code.

Education

Certificate of Higher Education, of Zaragoza Spain 2005 Java Development SL-275, SunMicrosystem 2007

Algorithms: Design and Analysis, 2013. Coursera

Cryptography I, 2013. Coursera

Startup Engineering 2013. Coursera Big Data Spark Foundations - IBM - 2015

Big Data - Programming - IBM - 2015

DEV 360 - Apache Spark Essentials - MapR Technologies - 2015

HDE 100 - Apache Hadoop Essentials - MapR Technologies - 2015

DEV 301 - Developing Hadoop Applications - MapR Technologies - 2015

HDE 100 - Apache Hadoop Essentials - MapR Technologies

Master's Degree (Master business administration), CEUPE 2015. Madrid Spain